<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Ddsolrad</title>

  <para></para>

  <section>
    <title>Description</title>

    <para>This component has two functions. One is to distribute measured or
    estimated solar radiation values for a horizontal surface to the slope and
    aspect combination of each HRU. The second is to estimate missing solar
    radiation data.</para>

    <para>Observed daily shortwave radiation (<code>solrad</code>) expressed
    in langleys per day (ly/d) can be input directly or estimated from daily
    air-temperature and precipitation data for watersheds where it is not
    available. <code>solrad</code>, measured on a horizontal surface, is
    adjusted to estimate <code>swrad</code>, the daily shortwave radiation
    received on the slope-aspect combination of each HRU. <code>swrad</code>
    is computed by:</para>

    <equation>
      <m:math display="block">
        <m:mrow>
          <m:mi>swrad</m:mi>

          <m:mo>=</m:mo>

          <m:mrow>
            <m:mrow>
              <m:mo>(</m:mo>

              <m:mrow>
                <m:mi>solrad</m:mi>

                <m:mo>×</m:mo>

                <m:mrow>
                  <m:mfrac>
                    <m:mi>radpl_potsw</m:mi>

                    <m:mi>horad</m:mi>
                  </m:mfrac>
                </m:mrow>
              </m:mrow>

              <m:mo>)</m:mo>
            </m:mrow>

            <m:mo>/</m:mo>

            <m:mi>radpl_cossl</m:mi>
          </m:mrow>
        </m:mrow>
      </m:math>
    </equation>

    <para>where</para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>radpl_potsw</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>the daily potential solar radiation for the slope and aspect
          of a radiation plane (ly),</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>horad</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>daily potential solar radiation for a horizontal surface (ly),
          and</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>radpl_cossl</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>the cosine of the radiation plane slope</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

    <para>Tables consisting of daily estimates of the potential (clear sky)
    short-wave solar radiation for each radiation plane
    (<code>radpl_potsw</code>) are computed on the basis of hours between
    sunrise and sunset for each Julian day of the year in module Soltab.java.
    The potential short-wave solar radiation is also computed for each Julian
    day of the year for a horizontal plane at the centroid of the modeled
    basin (<code>horad</code>). Daily values of <code>radpl_potsw</code> and
    <code>horad</code> are calculated using a combination of methods described
    in Meeus (1999), Lee (1963), and Swift (1976).</para>

    <para>For missing days or periods of record, <code>solrad</code> can be
    estimated using an air temperature / degree-day relationship described by
    Leaf and Brink (1973). This method was developed for a section of the
    Rocky Mountain Region of the United States. It appears most applicable to
    regions where predominantly clear skies prevail on days without
    precipitation. The method is shown graphically in the coaxial relation of
    <xref linkend="dday_temp" />. A daily maximum temperature is entered in
    the X-axis of part A and intersects the appropriate month curve. From this
    intersection point, one moves horizontally across the degree-day
    coefficient axis and intersects the curve in part B. From this point, the
    ratio of actual-to-potential radiation for a horizontal surface
    (<code>solf</code>) can be obtained.</para>

    <para><figure>
        <title xml:id="dday_temp">Example of coaxial relationship for
        estimating shortwave solar radiation from maximum daily air
        temperature developed for northwestern Colorado.</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="dday_rad.jpg" xml:id="dd"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure></para>

    <para>An estimate of solrad is then computed by:</para>

    <equation>
      <m:math display="block">
        <m:mrow>
          <m:mi>solrad</m:mi>

          <m:mo>=</m:mo>

          <m:mrow>
            <m:mi>solf</m:mi>

            <m:mo>×</m:mo>

            <m:mrow>
              <m:mrow>
                <m:mo>horad</m:mo>
              </m:mrow>
            </m:mrow>
          </m:mrow>
        </m:mrow>
      </m:math>
    </equation>

    <para>The ratio <code>solf</code> is developed for days without
    precipitation; thus, the computed <code>solrad</code> is for dry days.
    <code>solrad</code> for days with precipitation is computed by multiplying
    the dry day <code>solrad</code> times a precipitation correction factor
    <code>ppt_adj</code>. <code>ppt_adj</code> is determined based on the
    maximum air temperature (<code>tmax</code>) measured at the basin index
    temperature station (<code>basin_tsta</code>) on the day with
    precipitation and the current month. If <code>tmax</code> is greater than
    or equal to the monthly parameter <code>tmax_index</code>, then
    <code>ppt_adj</code> is computed by:</para>

    <equation>
      <m:math display="block">
        <m:mrow>
          <m:mi>ppt_adj</m:mi>

          <m:mo>=</m:mo>

          <m:mrow>
            <m:mrow>
              <m:mrow>
                <m:mo>(</m:mo>

                <m:mrow>
                  <m:mi>radadj_slope</m:mi>

                  <m:mo>×</m:mo>

                  <m:mi>tdif</m:mi>
                </m:mrow>

                <m:mo>)</m:mo>
              </m:mrow>

              <m:mo>+</m:mo>
            </m:mrow>

            <m:mi>radadj_intcp</m:mi>
          </m:mrow>
        </m:mrow>
      </m:math>
    </equation>

    <para>where tdif is the difference between <code>tmax</code> and
    <code>tmax_index</code>.</para>

    <para>If <code>tmax</code> is less than <code>tmax_index</code> then
    <code>ppt_adj</code> is set equal to a user-defined constant
    <code>radj_wppt</code> for the period October through April or
    <code>radj_sppt</code> for the period May through September. The use of
    <code>tmax_index</code> is an attempt to distinguish between days where
    precipitation is convective in origin and days where precipitation is
    frontal in origin. Days with typically short convective storms may have
    more solar radiation than those days with frontal storms. The assumption
    is that for each month a maximum temperature threshold value can be used
    to distinguish between these storm types.</para>

    <para>The input parameters required to use this procedure are the slope
    (<code>dday_slope</code>) and the y-intercept (<code>dday_intcp</code>) of
    the line that expresses the relationship between monthly maximum air
    temperature and a degree-day coefficient (<code>dd</code>) (<xref
    linkend="dday_temp" />). <code>dd</code> is computed by:</para>

    <equation>
      <m:math display="block">
        <m:mrow>
          <m:mi>dd</m:mi>

          <m:mo>=</m:mo>

          <m:mrow>
            <m:mrow>
              <m:mo>(</m:mo>

              <m:mrow>
                <m:mi>dday_slope</m:mi>

                <m:mo>×</m:mo>

                <m:mi>tmax</m:mi>
              </m:mrow>

              <m:mo>)</m:mo>
            </m:mrow>

            <m:mo>+</m:mo>

            <m:mi>dday_intcp</m:mi>
          </m:mrow>
        </m:mrow>
      </m:math>
    </equation>

    <para>where <code>tmax</code> is the observed daily maximum air
    temperature. The dd-solf relationship of <xref linkend="dday_temp" /> is
    assumed constant.</para>

    <para>Monthly values of <code>dday_slope</code> and
    <code>dday_intcp</code> can be estimated from historic air- temperature
    and solar-radiation data. One method is to make monthly plots of
    <code>tmax</code> versus their daily degree-day coefficients,
    <code>dd</code>, for days without precipitation. The <code>dd</code>
    values for this plot are computed using <xref linkend="dday_temp" /> and
    the daily <code>solf</code> ratios computed from historic data. A set of
    monthly lines then can be drawn through these points either visually or
    with linear- regression techniques. If there is a large difference in
    elevation between the climate station on the watershed and the station
    with radiation data, the air-temperature data associated with the
    radiation data should be adjusted to the elevation of the study-basin
    climate station.</para>

    <para>A more rapid and coarse procedure is to establish two points for
    each monthly line using some average values. One point for each month is
    estimated using the average <code>solf</code> and average maximum
    temperature for days without precipitation. The second point is estimated
    using the maximum observed temperature for each month and a
    <code>dd</code> value of 15. Using this second procedure, curves shown in
    part A of <xref linkend="dday_temp" /> were estimated for a region in
    northwest Colorado. Estimates of <code>radj_wppt</code> and
    <code>radj_sppt</code> are obtained from the radiation record.
    <code>radj_wppt</code> is the ratio of <code>solf</code> for days with
    precipitation to days without precipitation over the October through April
    period. <code>radj_sppt</code> is the ratio of <code>solf</code> for days
    with precipitation to days without precipitation over the May through
    September period</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>References</title>

    <para><bibliolist>
        <bibliomixed>Leaf, C. F., and Brink, G. E., 1973, Hydrologic
        simulation model of Colorado subalpine forest: U.S. Department of
        Agriculture, Forest Service Research Paper RM-107, 23 p.</bibliomixed>
      </bibliolist></para>

    <para><bibliolist>
        <bibliomixed>Leavesley, G. H., Lichty, R. W., Troutman, B. M., and
        Saindon, L. G., 1983, Precipitation-runoff modeling system--user's
        manual: U. S. Geological Survey Water Resources Investigations report
        83-4238, 207 p.</bibliomixed>
      </bibliolist></para>

    <para><bibliolist>
        <bibliomixed>Lee, R., 1963, Evaluation of solar beam irradiation as a
        climatic parameter of mountain watersheds: Colorado State University
        Hydrology Papers, no. 2, 50 p.</bibliomixed>
      </bibliolist></para>

    <para><bibliolist>
        <bibliomixed>Meeus, J., 1999, Astronomical Algorithms: Richmond, Va.,
        Willmann-Bell, Inc., 477 p.</bibliomixed>
      </bibliolist></para>

    <para><bibliolist>
        <bibliomixed>Swift, Lloyd W., Jr., 1976, Algorithm for solar radiation
        on mountain slopes: Water Resources Research, v. 12, no. 1, p.
        108-112.</bibliomixed>
      </bibliolist></para>
  </section>
</section>
