<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Smbal</title>

  <para></para>

  <section>
    <title>Description</title>

    <para>Soil moisture accounting is performed as the algebraic summation of
    all moisture accretions to, and depletions from, the active soil profile.
    Depletions include evapotranspiration and recharge to the subsurface and
    groundwater reservoirs. Accretions are rainfall and snowmelt infiltration.
    The depth of the active soil profile is considered to be the average
    rooting depth of the predominant vegetation on the HRU. The maximum
    available water holding capacity of the soil zone,
    <code>soil_moist_max</code>, is the difference between field capacity and
    wilting point of the profile. The active soil profile is divided into two
    layers. The upper layer is termed the recharge zone and the lower layer is
    termed the lower zone. The recharge zone is user-definable as to depth and
    maximum available water-holding capacity, <code>soil_rechr_max</code>. The
    maximum available water-holding capacity of the lower zone is the
    difference between <code>soil_moist_max</code> and
    <code>soil_rechr_max</code>. Losses from the recharge zone occur from
    evaporation and transpiration; they occur only as transpiration from the
    lower zone.</para>

    <para>First, infiltration from rainfall or snowmelt, <code>infil</code>,
    is added to the soil zone. Water in excess of <code>soil_moist_max</code>
    is distributed to the subsurface and groundwater reservoirs. The excess is
    first used to satisfy the maximum groundwater-recharge,
    <code>soil_to_gw</code>, and any remaining excess
    (<code>soil_to_ssr</code>) is added to the subsurface reservoir associated
    with the HRU.</para>

    <para>Actual evapotranspiration, <code>hru_actet</code>, is the computed
    rate of water loss, which reflects the availability of water to satisfy
    <code>potet</code>. When available water is non-limiting,
    <code>hru_actet</code> equals <code>potet</code>. Evaporation of
    intercepted water, <code>intcp_evap</code>, evaporation from impervious
    area retention storage, <code>imperv_evap</code>, and
    evaporation/sublimation from a snowpack, <code>snow_evap</code>, are first
    used to satisfy <code>potet</code>, in that order. Remaining
    <code>potet</code> demand then is applied to the soil-zone storage.
    <code>perv_actet</code> is computed separately for the recharge zone and
    the lower zone using the unsatisfied demand and the ratio of currently
    available water in the soil zone to its maximum available water-holding
    capacity. For the recharge zone, this ratio is <inlineequation>
        <m:math display="inline">
          <m:mfrac>
            <m:mi>soil_rechr</m:mi>

            <m:mi>soil_rechr_max</m:mi>
          </m:mfrac>
        </m:math>
      </inlineequation>. For the lower zone, the ratio <inlineequation>
        <m:math display="inline">
          <m:mfrac>
            <m:mi>soil_moist</m:mi>

            <m:mi>soil_moist_max</m:mi>
          </m:mfrac>
        </m:math>
      </inlineequation> is used. The <code>perv_actet</code> for the recharge
    zone is first used to satisfy <code>potet</code>; any remaining demand is
    attempted to be met from the lower zone. HRU soils are designated as being
    predominantly sand, loam or clay, using parameter <code>soil_type</code>.
    The potential-actual relations for these soil types as a function of the
    soil-water ratio are shown in (Zahner, 1967). <code>hru_actet</code> is
    computed as the area weighted average of <code>perv_actet</code> and
    <code>imperv_evap</code>.</para>

    <para></para>

    <figure>
      <title>Soil-water withdrawal functions for evapotranspirtation.</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="smav-aet.png"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>This module also computes basin weighted averages,
    <code>basin_actet</code>, <code>basin_soil_moist</code>, and
    <code>basin_soil_rechr</code>.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>References</title>

    <para><bibliolist>
        <bibliomixed>Leavesley, G. H., Lichty, R. W., Troutman, B. M., and
        Saindon, L. G., 1983, Precipitation-runoff modeling system--user's
        manual: U. S. Geological Survey Water Resources Investigations report
        83-4238, 207 p.</bibliomixed>
      </bibliolist></para>

    <para><bibliolist>
        <bibliomixed>Zahner, R., 1967, Refinement in empirical functions for
        realistic soil-moisture regimes under forest cover, in Sopper, W. E.,
        and Lull, H. W., eds., International Symposium of Forest Hydrology:
        New York, Pergamon Press, p. 261-274</bibliomixed>
      </bibliolist></para>
  </section>
</section>
